Guide to the Sugg Family and McDonald Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Sugg and McDonald family papers
1850-1973
WA MSS S-2885
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
50.1
(56 boxes)
This collection documents the Sugg family and McDonald family in Sonora, California, circa 1850-1973. Papers in the collection include correspondence, financial records, school records, recipes, photographs, and scrapbooks, as well as material related to collecting postage stamps. A group of papers also document the relationship between the Sugg family and George W. Nicol, a superior court judge in Tuolumne County, 1891-1922. Photographs in the collection consist chiefly of family portraits and snapshots, as well as examples of news photography created by Vernon McDonald for the Modesto Herald newspaper and Associated Press. The collection also includes books and printed material accumulated by the family.
Sugg Family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Robert Brennan on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Sugg Family and McDonald Family
The Sugg family and McDonald family were prominent African American families in Sonora, California. The progenitor of both families, William Sugg (1828-1889) was born a slave in Raleigh, North Carolina. Around 1850, he worked as a muleteer and bullwhacker traveling from Texas to Merced, California, with his master Francis Trale. In June 1854, Trale manumitted Sugg for one dollar. As a free black man, Sugg worked as a harness maker and teamster.
In 1855, Sugg married Mary Elizabeth Snelling (1839-1915). She was born in Johnson City, Missouri, the daughter of Julia Snelling (born circa 1800), a slave formerly owned by the William Snelling family, the founders of Snelling, California. In 1851, Mary and her mother relocated to California with the Snelling family.
In 1857, William Sugg built a three-room brick-faced adobe house at 37 Theall Street in Sonora; in 1885, a multi-storied and wood framed addition added seven bedrooms to the residence. Around the turn of the twentieth century, the Sugg home provided rooms to overflow guests from local hotels.
William and Mary Sugg had eleven children: Julia "Fannie" Sugg (born circa 1856), Sarah Ann Sugg (circa 1857-1914), Elizabeth Francis Sugg (born circa 1858), Mary Anita Sugg (circa 1859-1917); William Sugg (1862-1908), Rosa Adele Sugg (1865-1941), Napoleon "Poli" Bonaparte Sugg (1867-1944), Alonzo Sugg (circa 1869-1923), Nellie Sugg (1871-1959), Melpomene "Babe" Sugg (1874-1950) and Ernest Alaric Sugg (1876-1952). In 1877, the elder William Sugg relocated to Merced, where he operated a harness business until his death.
Only two of the children in the Sugg family married. In 1897, the younger William Sugg married Alice Elebeck (born 1869); they divorced two years later. In 1906, Rosa married Daniel William McDonald (1866-1952), and they had two sons, Earl Sugg McDonald (born 1903) and Vernon "Scoop" Sugg McDonald (1906-1982).
In 1912, Rosa, Earl, and Vernon McDonald relocated to Sonora and lived in the Sugg House. Earl reportedly moved to Sacramento, while Vernon remained in Sonora and became a correspondent with the Modesto Herald and Associated Press. Vernon also served as a sergeant in the United States Army during World War II.
In 1979, Robert Brennan purchased the Sugg family home, while Vernon McDonald continued to live there until his death in May 1982. In 1984, the Sugg House became a listed property on the National Register of Historic Places.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the Sugg and McDonald family of Sonora, California, circa 1850-1964. Papers in the collection include correspondence, financial records, school records, recipes, photographs, and scrapbooks, as well as material related to collecting postage stamps. A group of papers documents the relationship between the Sugg family and George W. Nicol, a superior court judge in Tuolumne County, 1891-1922. Photographs in the collection consist chiefly of family portraits and snapshots, as well as examples of news photography created by Vernon McDonald for the Modesto Herald newspaper and Associated Press. The collection also includes books and printed material accumulated by the family.
Arrangement
I. Papers, 1864-1962. II. Photographs, circa 1850-1973. III. Printed Material and Books, 1859-1964.
Modesto Herald; African Americans -- California -- Sonora; Historic sites -- California -- Sonora; Urban African Americans -- California -- Sonora; Sonora (Calif.); Sonora (Calif.) -- Social life and customs; Negatives (photographic); Postage stamps; Photographic prints; McDonald (Family); McDonald family; McDonald, Earl Sugg, 1903-; McDonald, Vernon Sugg, 1906-1982; Nicol, George W., -1922; Suggs family; Sugg, Alonzo, approximately 1869-1923; Sugg, Elizabeth Francis, approximately 1858-; Sugg, Ernest Alaric, 1876-1952; Sugg, Julia, approximately 1856-; Sugg, Mary Anita, approximately 1859-1917; Sugg, Mary Elizabeth Snelling, 1839-1915; Sugg, Melpomene, 1874-1950; Sugg, Napoleon Bonaparte, 1867-1944; Sugg, Nellie, 1871-1959; Sugg, Rosa Adele, 1865-1941; Sugg, Sarah Ann, approximately 1857-1914; Sugg, William, 1862-1908; Sugg, William, 1828-1889
- Papers, 1864-1962; Series I; 15.9; (20 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into nine subseries: Correspondence, Napoleon Sugg Papers, Financial Records, School Records, Scrapbooks, Family Material, Postage Stamp Collecting, Miscellaneous Material, and Oversize Material
  - Correspondence
    Scope and Contents
    This subseries consists of unsorted correspondence, as well as papers and correspondence related to George W. Nicol (died 1922), a superior court judge in Tuolumne County, 1891-1922
    - Correspondence, 1864-1962; 19 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1920-1949; 13 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1930-1939; 22 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1930-1959; 19 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1940-1943; 17 (Box 5)
    - Independent Order of Odd Fellows (IOOF) Correspondence, circa 1898-1899 (Box 6)
    - American Baptist Publication Society Correspondence, 1916-1922 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence and papers related to George W. Nicol, 1889-1921; 2 (Box 6)
    - Postcards, 1900-1930; 3 (Box 6)
  - Napoleon Sugg Papers
    Chiefly employment records related to Napoleon "Poli" Bonaparte Sugg. He worked as a teamster for various union locals in the Stockton area.
    - Union material and letters of inquiry, undated; 2 (Box 7)
    - Ledgers, photographs, and receipts, undated; 3 (Box 7)
    - Postcards, undated (Box 7)
  - Financial Records
    This subseries consists of unsorted financial records related to family businesses, as well as daily domestic life
    - Ledgers and account books, 1883-1925, undated; 17 (Box 8)
    - Receipts, 1858-1896; 10 (Box 8)
    - Receipts, 1900-1930, undated; 21 (Box 9)
    - Other financial records, 1867-1924, undated; 4 (Box 9)
  - School Records
    - School books and papers, 1878-1921, undated; 17 (Box 10)
    - School books and papers, 1894-1924, undated; 6 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbooks, circa 1932-1940 (Box 12)
      2 volumes
    - Scrapbooks, circa 1938-1940 (Box 13)
    - Scrapbook of sheet music, undated (Box 14)
  - Family Material
    - Family recipes and remedies, undated (Box 15)
    - Scrapbook of family recipes, undated (Box 15)
      1 volume
    - Book of notes, undated (Box 15)
    - Autograph albums, 1889 (Box 15)
    - Scrapbooks, undated (Box 15)
    - Book of Odds and Ends, undated (Box 15)
    - Wallets of Napoleon Sugg, undated (Box 15)
    - Pocket Books, 1896-1936; 2 (Box 15)
    - Order blanks, advertisements, etc. (Box 15)
    - Map and Day Book covers (Box 15)
    - Cruise souvenir and envelopes, 1908, 1901-1907 (Box 15)
    - Membership cards, 1940-1949 (Box 15)
  - Postage Stamp Collecting
    Biographical/Historical note
    Vernon Sugg McDonald was a charter member of the Tuolumne County Stamp Club.
    - Postage stamps, 1899-1960, undated; 17 (Box 16)
    - Stamp albums, circa 1900-1902; 2 (Box 17)
    - Postage stamp catalogs, 1936, undated; 4 (Box 17)
    - Newspaper clippings and material about stamp collecting, 1937-1938, undated (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous Material, 1898-1945, undated; 13 (Box 18)
    This subseries consists of unsorted and unidentified material
  - Oversize Material
    - Hotel visitors, 1896, 1894 (Box 19)
      Page from a ledger
    - Grammar school diploma for Melpomene Suggs, 1893 (Box 19)
    - Grammar school diploma for Earl Sugg McDonald, 1917 (Box 19)
- Photographs, circa 1850-1973; Series II; 6.4; (7 boxes)
  Series II consists of unsorted photographic material.
  - Cased photographs, circa 1850-1880 (Box 20)
    8 cased photographs
  - Framed photograph, undated (Box 20)
  - Lantern slides, undated (Box 20)
  - Photograph albums, circa 1860-1900 (Box 21)
    3 photograph albums
  - Photographic prints, circa 1894-1966, undated; 15 (Box 22)
  - Photographic prints, circa 1892-1965, undated; 6 (Box 23)
  - Photographic prints, 1949-1961, undated; 10 (Box 24)
  - Photographic negatives and photographic prints, undated; 16 (Box 25)
  - Photographic negatives, undated; 3 (Box 25)
  - Slides, 1949-1973, undated; 9 (Box 26)
  - Oversize Material
    - Photographic prints, 1898-1914 (Box 27)
    - Photograph album, circa 1903-1907 (Box 27)
    - Portrait of Melpomene Suggs, undated (Box 27)
    - Portrait of an unidentified male, undated (Box 27)
- Printed Material and Books, 1859-1964; Series III; 27.8; (29 boxes)
  Series III is organized into two subseries: Print Material and Boks.
  Series III consists of unsorted printed material and books collected by the Sugg family and McDonald family.
  - Printed Material
    - Family Bible, 1859 (Box 28)
    - The Bride's Cookbook, undated (Box 28)
    - The Cabinet Cookbook, 1937? (Box 28)
    - Recipe books and booklets, 1911-1941, undated; 4 (Box 28)
    - Household booklets, 1904-1926, undated (Box 28)
    - Medical booklets, 1860-1871, undated (Box 28)
    - Informational booklets, 1915-1932, undated (Box 28)
    - Game and toy booklets, 1895-1940 (Box 28)
    - Music books, 1895, undated (Box 28)
    - Poetry books, 1894-1938 (Box 28)
    - Devotional booklets, 1905, undated (Box 28)
    - Official Lawn Tennis Guide, 1933 (Box 28)
    - California Historian, 1964 January-June; 2 (Box 28)
    - California Football Programs, 1931, 1938 (Box 28)
    - Chesterfield's Letter Writing and Complete Book of Etiquette, 1857 (Box 29)
    - Webster's Reliable Dictionary for Home, School and Office, 1911 (Box 29)
    - Dictionary, undated (Box 29)
    - Aunt Lindy, 1893 (Box 29)
      1 folder
    - The Reason Why the Colored American is Not in the World's Columbian Exposition, undated (Box 29)
    - History of Marie Antoinette of France, 1864 (Box 29)
    - The Homing Instinct, 1913 (Box 29)
    - The Brass Check: A Study of American Journalism, undated (Box 29)
    - Advanced Arithmetic, undated (Box 29)
    - The Caxtons, undated (Box 29)
    - The Fur Seal's Tooth, 1894 (Box 29)
    - Under Both Flags: An Illustrated Story of the Civil War, 1896 (Box 29)
    - The Great South: A Record of Journeys, 1875 (Box 29)
    - Periodicals and programs, 1879-1941 (Box 30)
    - Yearbook and booklets, 1928-1934 (Box 30)
    - Newspaper clippings, 4 (Box 30)
  - Books
    - The Book of Knowledge (Children's Encyclopedia), Volumes 1-10, circa 1912 (Box 31)
    - The Book of Knowledge (Children's Encyclopedia), Volumes 11-20, circa 1912 (Box 32)
    - The Chautauquan, Volumes 20-25, 1897 (Box 33)
    - Encyclopedia and reference, circa 1904-1976 (Box 34)
      9 volumes
    - Chambers Encyclopedia, Volumes 1-5, 1893 (Box 35)
    - Chambers Encyclopedia, Volumes 6-9, 1893 (Box 36)
    - Dictionaries, circa 1868-1948 (Box 37)
      6 volumes
    - Dictionaries, reference, and non-fiction, circa 1888-1937 (Box 38)
      11 volumes
    - Non-fiction and business, circa 1879-1957 (Box 39)
      10 volumes
    - Textbooks, circa 1863-1923 (Box 40)
      25 volumes
    - Textbooks and cookbooks, circa 1868-1940 (Box 41)
      26 volumes
    - Instruction and other, circa 1880-1936 (Box 42)
    - Poetry and literature, circa 1874-1916 (Box 43)
      21 volumes
    - Literature, circa 1853-1969 (Box 44)
      17 volumes
    - Medicine and biography, circa 1866-1934 (Box 45)
    - History, circa 1870-1919 (Box 46)
      8 volumes
    - History, circa 1849-1938 (Box 47)
      15 volumes
    - Music, circa 1863-1914 (Box 48)
      12 volumes
    - Music, circa 1894-1909 (Box 49)
      17 folders
    - Young adult and humor, circa 1889-1936 (Box 50)
      18 volumes
    - Fiction, circa 1855-1955 (Box 51)
    - Fiction, circa 1886-1951 (Box 52)
    - Bibles and devotional literature, circa 1852-1952 (Box 53)
    - Fragile books, circa 1890-1915 (Box 54)
    - Fragile books, circa 1863-1900 (Box 55)
      16 volumes
    - Oversize sheet music, 13 (Box 56)